<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<tei>
    <teiHeader xml:lang="en">
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Introduction to <emph rend="italic">LITTLE
                    WARS</emph></title>
                <editor key="lepianka">Nigel Lepianka</editor>
                <editor key="stover">Deanna Stover</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Creation and Encoding</resp>
                    <name xml:id="ed">Nigel Lepianka and Deanna Stover</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2016</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>Scholarly Editing: The Annual of the Association for Documentary
                    Editing</authority>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>http://www.scholarlyediting.org</addrLine>
                </address>
                <publisher>Association for Documentary Editing</publisher>
                <publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
                <distributor>
                    <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>http://cdrh.unl.edu</addrLine>
                    </address>
                </distributor>
                <date>2016</date>
                <availability>
                    <p>Scholarly Editing: The Annual of the Association for Documentary Editing is
                        freely distributed by the Association for Documentary Editing and the Center
                        for Digital Research in the Humanities at the University of Nebraska-Lincoln
                        and licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike
                        3.0 Unported License</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="j">Scholarly Editing: The Annual of the Association for Documentary
                    Editing</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name xml:id="ag">Amanda Gailey</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name xml:id="awj">Andrew Jewell</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name xml:id="ng">Nicole Gray</name>
                </respStmt>
                <idno type="vol">38</idno>
                <idno type="ISSN">2167-1257</idno>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <note>Born digital.</note>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change who="lepianka" when="2016-10-17">Begin encoding of introduction.</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <p>H.G. Wells (1866-1946) published two books about play with miniatures, first
                        <emph rend="italic">Floor Games</emph> in 1911 and then <emph rend="italic"
                        >Little Wars</emph> in 1913. In the first, Wells explains the supplies
                    needed to create a world on the nursery floor and dramatizes his sons’ play;
                        <emph rend="italic">Little Wars</emph>, however, provides a more complex,
                    codified game. More importantly, <emph rend="italic">Little Wars</emph> was
                    unprecedented. As Jon Peterson notes, it was the first time “miniature wargame
                    rules [were] marketed in book form to the general public.”<ptr target="#note1"
                        xml:id="nr1" n="1"/>
                    <emph rend="italic">Little Wars</emph> continues to be influential on modern
                    gaming: the book has become the norm for popular role-playing game rulebooks
                    like <emph rend="italic">Dungeons &amp; Dragons</emph>. Although <emph
                        rend="italic">Little Wars</emph> has stayed in print since its first
                    publication, and later editions feature forewords by influential figures
                    including writer Isaac Asimov and <emph rend="italic">Dungeons &amp;
                        Dragons</emph> creator Gary Gygax, to date there has not been a critical
                    scholarly edition of the text.</p>
                <p> As a rulebook, the primary goal of <emph rend="italic">Little Wars</emph> is, in
                    the end, to produce play (even if it is play with an ideological bent--in this
                    case, pacifism). However, the text is far more than a straightforward account of
                    rules. As Esther MacCallum-Stewart has pointed out, <emph rend="italic">Little
                        Wars</emph> consists of three sections: an early version of the “development
                    diary” (a contemporary invention where game designers describe the evolution of
                    their designs) in which Wells describes how he modifies the rules through
                    repeated play (chapter two); a rules section (chapter three); and an “example of
                    play” detailing Wells’s successful “Battle of Hook’s Farm” (chapter four).<ptr
                        target="#note2" xml:id="nr2" n="2"/> Black-and-white photos of play and
                    set-up taken by Wells’s wife and comic marginal illustrations by J.R. Sinclair
                    accompany the text. The illustrations, photos, and text all interact, which is
                    partially why current digital transcripts that fail to include the marginal
                    illustrations do not accurately represent <emph rend="italic">Little
                    Wars</emph>. The sets Wells builds to stage his wars are incredibly detailed,
                    and many of the photos are shot in a way that makes them seem lifelike; the few
                    photos featuring Wells and his opponent, Jerome K. Jerome, are almost shocking
                    in comparison. The marginal illustrations similarly depict both animated toys in
                    naturalistic settings and lifeless figurines using books for cover or being
                    moved by a player’s hand. </p>
                <p> Throughout <emph rend="italic">Little Wars</emph>, this tension between game and
                    fiction exists. When describing the Battle of Hook’s Farm, Wells adopts a
                    persona and what follows is more like a short story than simply a description of
                    play: <ab>And suddenly your author changes. He changes into what perhaps he
                        might have been--under different circumstances. His inky fingers become
                        large, manly hands, his drooping scholastic back stiffens, his elbows go
                        out, his etiolated complexion corrugates and darkens, his moustaches
                        increase and grow and spread, and curl up horribly; a large, red scar, a
                        sabre cut, grows lurid over one eye. He expands--all over he
                        expands.</ab><ptr target="#note3" xml:id="nr3" n="3"/> Narrating as a
                    general, it is here where we can begin to see elements of modern role-playing
                    games (RPGs) where players adopt personas. Wells clearly sees his games as
                    participatory literature. The title to chapter six, “Ending with a Sort of
                    Challenge” is joined by an illustration of a bookcase labeled “Little Wars,”
                    topped with a general’s bust, and featuring 19 volumes of books--books that may
                    depict his readers’ wars as much as his own. And yet, potential stories must
                    still exist within a set of rules. Like in modern RPGs, prescribed guidelines
                    add structure to a game; limitations allow for more interesting play because
                    players must strategically and creatively navigate through a fixed framework to
                    win. In the end, as many gamers will agree, the story that plays out as a result
                    of these rules is as satisfying as any victory. </p>
                <p>While this text is much more than rules, our approach to this critical edition is
                    meant to frame the text around the rules and suggestions of gameplay prescribed
                    in chapter 3 in order to highlight the participatory nature of <emph
                        rend="italic">Little Wars</emph>. While a narrative in its own right, <emph
                        rend="italic">Little Wars</emph> gives its readers and players (mutually
                    inclusive groups that they are) the chance to create their own narratives. It
                    could be argued that other works or texts could allow for such a phenomenon, and
                    we would not presume <emph rend="italic">Little Wars</emph> and other game
                    manuals to be the sole purveyors of such a productive element of literary works,
                    however, game manuals like <emph rend="italic">Little Wars</emph> presume as
                    their <emph rend="italic">raison d’etre</emph> that the game will be played.
                    Readers will interact with and build on the initial text, creating narratives
                    that even Wells at his most fantastical could not predict. In addition, we see
                    this edition as adding to the growing scholarly body on games and gaming. Part
                    of our purpose here is to begin a conversation about how to use current TEI
                    standards to encode rules. We have explained our choices below and hope that our
                    decisions will continue to be refined as similar projects develop.</p>
                <p>In order to emphasize that <emph rend="italic">Little Wars</emph> is both a
                    readable text <emph rend="italic">and</emph> a playable game, we have also
                    included XML encoded streamlined rules. Wells’s rules are often accompanied by
                    asides and narratives, and we felt that simplifying and clarifying the rules
                    would help make gameplay more accessible. We have chosen not to include any of
                    the rules Wells sketched out in the appendix for adjusting <emph rend="italic"
                        >Little Wars</emph> for military training in preference of highlighting
                    Wells’s original creation. We invite readers to engage with <emph rend="italic"
                        >Little Wars</emph> by creating their own miniature battles. As Wells
                    himself explains: “It is for you, dear reader, now to get a floor, a friend,
                    some soldiers and some guns, and show by a groveling devotion your appreciation
                    of this noble and beautiful gift of limitless game that I have given you.”<ptr
                        target="#note4" xml:id="nr4" n="4"/>
                </p>
            </div>

            <div>
                <head>The Context</head>
                <p>Wells’s <emph rend="italic">Floor Games</emph> and <emph rend="italic">Little
                        Wars</emph> come out of a contemporary growing cultural interest in toy
                    soldiers (also referred to as miniatures, a term which allows for a more varied
                    understanding of small figurines used for play or display). The Prussian
                    invention, <emph rend="italic">kriegspiel</emph>, was a watershed moment for the
                    creation and use of structured systems for simulating war and helped to spur the
                    growth of toy industries at the turn of the twentieth century. <emph
                        rend="italic">Little Wars</emph> represents Wells’s expansion and response
                    to the <emph rend="italic">kriegspiel</emph> or wargame concept. However, the
                    books were not Wells’s ideas. <emph rend="italic">Floor Games</emph> and <emph
                        rend="italic">Little Wars</emph> came about after a seemingly small
                    publisher, Frank Palmer, reached out to Wells (already an established and
                    popular author at this point) and asked him to write a book about games for
                    children. Wells obviously agreed. Although <emph rend="italic">Little
                        Wars</emph> would be published by Palmer in 1913, it was first serialized
                    (without J.R. Sinclair’s illustrations but under the copyright of Frank Palmer)
                    in <emph rend="italic">The Windsor Magazine: An Illustrated Monthly for Men and
                        Women</emph> beginning in December 1912.</p>
                <p>Palmer recruited Wells after reading the author’s semi-autobiographical and
                    controversial novel <emph rend="italic">The New Machiavelli</emph>, first
                    serialized in 1910. The novel features multiple references to the wargames the
                    main character, Dick Remington, and his friend Britten<ptr target="#note5"
                        xml:id="nr5" n="5"/> would play: <ab>We developed a war game of our own at
                        Britten’s home with nearly a couple of hundred lead soldiers, some excellent
                        spring cannons that short hard and true at six yards, hills of books and a
                        constantly elaborated set of rules. For some months that occupied an immense
                        proportion of our leisure. Some of the battles lasted several days. We kept
                        the game a profound secret from the other fellows. They would not have
                            understood.<ptr target="#note6" xml:id="nr6" n="6"/></ab> However,
                    unlike Dick Remington, Palmer knew that “other fellows” would certainly
                    understand the appeal of staging little wars--he was tapping into an already
                    popular and ever-growing market. </p>
                <p>In 1893 William Britain had revolutionized the toy world by introducing hollow
                    miniatures, making them more affordable. Due in part to the general increase in
                    leisure time, literacy, and income amongst the middle class, toys became a
                    staple during the latter half of the nineteenth century;<ptr target="#note7"
                        xml:id="nr7" n="7"/> in fact, Kenneth Brown identifies, in particular, a
                    “toy soldier craze” in the two decades leading up to the Great War, or as we
                    know it, World War I.<ptr target="#note8" xml:id="nr8" n="8"/> Notably, while
                    children were certainly a part of the intended market, they were not necessarily
                    the only intended audience. Many adults played with miniatures with and without
                    children, and Wells was clearly not writing to an exclusively child audience.
                    The venue in which <emph rend="italic">Little Wars</emph> was published, <emph
                        rend="italic">Windsor Magazine</emph>, was for “men and women,” and Wells
                    consistently speaks to adults throughout the rulebook. </p>
                <p>The subtitle of <emph rend="italic">Little Wars</emph> itself, “A game for Boys
                    from twelve years of age to one hundred and fifty and for that more intelligent
                    sort of girl who likes boys’ games and books,” explicitly highlights the belief
                    that adults (primarily male--a misconception about gaming that still exists
                    today) could enjoy these games. This subtitle is even more interesting after
                    realizing that Wells’s oldest son George Philip, was not quite twelve at the
                    time <emph rend="italic">Little Wars</emph> was first published.<ptr
                        target="#note9" xml:id="nr9" n="9"/> Moreover, Kimberley Reynolds points out
                    that “there is, in fact, a notable absence of children in the photographs that
                    illustrate <emph rend="italic">Little Wars</emph>”--four of the photos do
                    however feature Wells and his opponent Jerome K. Jerome, giants in comparison to
                    the miniature world they are creating. And Wells was not the only literary
                    figure involved in wargames. Besides his companion Jerome, we know that Robert
                    Louis Stevenson and others enjoyed playing with miniatures.<ptr target="#note10"
                        xml:id="nr10" n="10"/> Wells also claims to have played wargames with
                    various political leaders, including Winston Churchill.<ptr target="#note11"
                        xml:id="nr11" n="11"/></p>
                <p>In any case, Wells’s wargame rules continue to be considered the most influential
                    of the time. Many scholars have commented on how Wells’s rulebooks nearly
                    function as advertising for William Britain’s toys. J.R. Sinclair’s
                    illustrations certainly resemble contemporary toy soldier advertisements. In
                    fact, at the end of <emph rend="italic">Floor Games</emph>, where Wells focuses
                    on the miniature worlds his sons create rather than any form of rule-based play,
                    he writes: “And of the war game I must either write volumes or nothing. Some
                    day, perhaps, I will write a great book about the war game and tell of battles
                    and campaigns and strategy and tactics. But this time I set out merely to tell
                    of the ordinary joys of playing with the floor, and to gird improvingly and
                    usefully at toymakers.”<ptr target="#note12" xml:id="nr12" n="12"/> James Opie
                    suggests that Wells’s girding in <emph rend="italic">Floor Games</emph> was
                    successful, as Wells calls for a larger variety of citizen miniatures, something
                    Britain delivered in 1912 with the Civilians set 169. Opie even goes so far as
                    to “wonder if contact [between Wells and Britain] ensued, and <emph
                        rend="italic">Little Wars</emph> was the result.”<ptr target="#note13"
                        xml:id="nr13" n="13"/> In many ways, Wells <emph rend="italic">was</emph>
                    advertising miniatures; he saw playing war as a practice that might discourage
                    war, a particularly timely purpose considering Wells published <emph
                        rend="italic">Little Wars</emph> just a year before the start of the first
                    World War. </p>
            </div>

            <div>
                <head>Wells and War</head>
                <p>What Wells knew as the “Great War” was clearly on his mind as he was writing
                        <emph rend="italic">Little Wars</emph>. He repeatedly distinguishes his
                    games from reality, even so far as to believe that <emph rend="italic">Little
                        Wars</emph> might function as a deterrent for the “Real Thing.”
                    Specifically, he imagines that players of his game would begin to see the
                    horrors and impracticality of real warfare: “I have never yet met in little
                    battle any military gentleman, any captain, major, colonel, general, or eminent
                    commander, who did not presently get into difficulties and confusions among even
                    the elementary rules of the Battle. You have only to play at Little Wars three
                    or four times to realise just what a blundering thing Great War must be.”<ptr
                        target="#note14" xml:id="nr14" n="14"/> For this reason, Jon Peterson
                    qualifies <emph rend="italic">Little Wars</emph>: “Nominally it describes a
                    game, but it served just as well as a polemic.”<ptr target="#note15"
                        xml:id="nr15" n="15"/></p>
                <p>Wells’s pacifism makes his choice to publish <emph rend="italic">Little
                        Wars</emph> particularly interesting, but Wells’s was an imperialistic
                    pacifism. Although not included in this edition, <emph rend="italic">Floor
                        Games</emph> complicates Wells’s relationship with violence. He describes
                    his and his son’s world-building play thus: “We land and alter things, and build
                    and rearrange, and hoist paper flags on pins, and subjugate populations, and
                    confer all the blessings of civilisation upon these lands.”<ptr target="#note16"
                        xml:id="nr16" n="16"/> Subjugating populations implies violence, but with
                    very little risk to England’s well being. Rather than decrying war in and of
                    itself, Wells is reacting to fears about modern warfare between world powers
                    rather than any violence associated with Imperial conquest. Much of this fear
                    seems to stem from rapidly evolving weapon technologies. Just before he wrote
                        <emph rend="italic">Floor Games</emph> in 1911, Wells admitted that “we have
                    over-developed war.” In fact, many of his writings foretold the destruction of
                    man through war. And while <emph rend="italic">Little Wars</emph> was by far his
                    first war “game,” “by the time the world went to war in August 1914, H.G. Wells
                    had already fought a goodly number of major wars, most of them global in scope,
                    in his scientific romances, short stories, and essays.”<ptr target="#note17"
                        xml:id="nr17" n="17"/> Wells was incredibly gifted at predicting future war
                    technologies, conceivably making the realities of a fast-approaching war all the
                    more terrifying for him. After all, he imagined what are essentially tanks in
                        <emph rend="italic">The Land Ironclad</emph> (1903), aerial warfare in <emph
                        rend="italic">The War in the Air</emph> (1908), and atomic bombs in <emph
                        rend="italic">The World Set Free</emph> (1914).</p>
                <p>Perhaps this fear is what made playing little wars so fascinating to Wells.
                    Peterson and others have pointed out how antiquated Wells’s battle rules are.
                    Unlike real battle, Wells modified his game tirelessly on developing a fair form
                    of war as shown in chapter two. One might say that <emph rend="italic">Little
                        Wars</emph> even offers up a utopian version of war since it works towards
                    setting up a battle amongst equals. The little wars staged according to Wells’s
                    rules are not representations of an Imperial Britain against indigenous peoples
                    resisting colonization, nor even are they battles of Waterloos, between two
                    distinct, yet Western, powers. Instead, <emph rend="italic">Little Wars</emph>
                    can be most accurately understood as a battle between two Englands.<ptr
                        target="#note18" xml:id="nr18" n="18"/> At all points, Wells constructs the
                    procedures of his game to indicate the necessary equality between Players A and
                    B. Even in cases where an advantage may be inferred, Wells considers and
                    implements rules to eliminate or mitigate those advantages. Aside from
                    determining the city designer (a privilege Wells also attempts to make more
                    equitable by allowing the other player to choose where the army enters), the
                    mechanics of <emph rend="italic">Little Wars</emph> are designed to help
                    eliminate chance: players receive an equal number of units although they can
                    choose the configuration (more cavalry versus more guns or infantry, etc.), who
                    all obey a mutual set of rules with little difference between the opposing
                    sides. Battle is also reliant on mutual trust; although players can use a
                    curtain to hide their set-up, the rest of the war is fought in the open and each
                    player is responsible for keeping track of time during their opponent’s turn. </p>
                <p>This egalitarian and trustful approach to warfare reflects Wells’s
                    romanticization of a simpler time within his rules. Peterson notes that <emph
                        rend="italic">Little Wars</emph> recalls “a romantic era of warfare, that of
                    a century before: a time when two uniformed armies in orderly columns conducted
                    the business of war under a common law of arms, in a bounded arena far from
                        civilians.”<ptr target="#note19" xml:id="nr19" n="19"/> Compared to the
                    threat of increasingly technological warfare, Wells’s wars are tame, simple, and
                    clean. Attacks rely almost completely on the aimed cannon-fire or capture; until
                    the appendix where Wells, with the help of Colonel Mark Sykes, develops a set of
                    rules that makes <emph rend="italic">Little Wars</emph> more effective as a
                    training mechanism, Wells does not make any instructions for arming the soldiers
                    with rifles. In fact, “in the <emph rend="italic">Little Wars</emph> systems
                    infantry and cavalry effectively fight in melee range,”<ptr target="#note20"
                        xml:id="nr20" n="20"/> an anachronistic decision that reflects Wells’s
                    anxieties about and dismissal of a more modern, technologically advanced
                    warfare.</p>
                <p>And yet, Wells's desire for <emph rend="italic">Little Wars</emph> to function as
                    a sort of substitution for war, whilst educating and providing entertainment,
                    necessitates that the little wars reflect, in some way, the complexities and
                    realities of a real war. Referencing proponents of war, Wells believed that “my
                    game is just as good as their game, and saner by reason of its size. Here is
                    War, done down to rational proportions, and yet out of the way of mankind.”<ptr
                        target="#note21" xml:id="nr21" n="21"/> Despite the possible annoyance of
                    toy war spilling out into the staircase,<ptr target="#note22" xml:id="nr22"
                        n="22"/> little wars were abstracted from reality. The game allowed for more
                    control than the looming Great War; it granted the players a feeling of agency
                    while also removing war simulation from any real world: “The miniature . . .
                    presents a diminutive, and thereby manipulatable, version of experience, a
                    version which is domesticated and protected from contamination. It marks the
                    pure body, the inorganic body of the machine and its repetition of a death that
                    is thereby not a death.”<ptr target="#note23" xml:id="nr23" n="23"/> Lacking any
                    visceral ends and capable of repeated play, Wells continuously reminds the
                    reader that these little toy soldiers and their little wars do not replicate
                    reality, even if they satisfy a desire for violence. Wells challenges the
                    realities of war through the very ability to reenact and reimagine battles and
                    scenery again and again. This combined with antiquated weapon technology allows
                    the warfare in <emph rend="italic">Little Wars</emph> to be relatively harmless
                    compared to the “Real Thing.” </p>
                <p>Famous for his “Imaginative Romances” and articles of social commentary,
                    publications that often forebode man’s destruction at the hands of increasingly
                    dangerous weapons, it is no surprise that Wells uses <emph rend="italic">Little
                        Wars</emph> to once more expound his beliefs: <ab>And if I might for a
                        moment trumpet! How much better is this amiable miniature than the Real
                        Thing! . . . Here is the premeditation, the thrill, the strain of
                        accumulating victory or disaster––and no smashed nor sanguinary bodies, no
                        shattered fine buildings nor devastated country sides, no petty cruelties,
                        none of that awful universal boredom and embitterment, that tiresome delay
                        or stoppage or embarrassment of every gracious bold, sweet, and charming
                        thing, that we who are old enough to remember a real modern war know to be
                        the reality of belligerence.<ptr target="#note24" xml:id="nr24" n="24"
                        /></ab> It is this idea of a modern war that Wells fears and tries to leave
                    out of his rulebook, an interesting but conscious choice for someone who
                    regularly incorporated technology into his writings. Asimov would later write in
                    his foreword to <emph rend="italic">Little Wars</emph>, “There is an air of
                    glamor and excitement about war--past wars, that is, that one need not actually
                    live through. The dangers and the daring and the gallant defeats and the clever
                    stratagems and the final triumph--what can replace it? In the absence of
                    reality, there is the driving desire to find a substitute.”<ptr target="#note25"
                        xml:id="nr25" n="25"/> With such a gifted imagination, perhaps in miniatures
                    Wells finally found a way to create a utopian version of war that (toy)
                    technology allowed rather than eliminated. </p>
                <p>However, Wells would go on to change his mind about the importance of wargames.
                    While in <emph rend="italic">Little Wars</emph> Wells imagines his games as “a
                    homeopathic remedy for the imaginative strategist,”<ptr target="#note26"
                        xml:id="nr26" n="26"/> twenty-one years later his autobiography laments how
                    the current educational system glamorizes war and socializes children to desire
                    to reconstruct it: “I think there is no natural bias towards bloodshed in
                    imaginative youngsters, but the only vivid and inspiring things that history fed
                    me with were campaigns and conquests.”<ptr target="#note27" xml:id="nr27" n="27"
                    /> His pre-World War I self saw wargames as an outlet, but the beginning of the
                    “Great War” affected his outlook: “Up to 1914, I found a lively interest in
                    playing a war game, with toy soldiers and guns, that recalled a peculiar quality
                    and pleasure of those early reveries.”<ptr target="#note28" xml:id="nr28" n="28"
                    /> In fact, Wells seems to have come to the belief that these games and the
                    culture that produced them were actually dangerous as opposed to an outlet. He
                    laments that “men in responsible positions” such as Winston Churchill, had
                    imaginations “built upon a similar framework” causing them to remain “puerile in
                    their political outlook.”<ptr target="#note29" xml:id="nr29" n="29"/> Instead,
                    Wells believes he has moved beyond his little wars: “I like to think I grew up
                    out of that stage somewhere between 1916 and 1920 and began to think about war
                    as a responsible adult should.”<ptr target="#note30" xml:id="nr30" n="30"/> Some
                    modern counterparts share a similar concern with violent video games.<ptr
                        target="#note31" xml:id="nr31" n="31"/>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head><emph rend="italic">Little Wars</emph> and Transmission</head>
                <p>Despite Wells recanting his belief that little wars could help curtail great
                    ones, many other wargamers have continued to see play as an outlet for violence.
                    In his foreword to a 2004 edition of <emph rend="italic">Little Wars</emph>,
                    tabletop gaming icon Gary Gygax admits to defending wargaming with an argument
                    very similar to Wells’s claim in <emph rend="italic">Little Wars</emph>; Gygax
                    explains that “miniature soldiers leave no widows or orphans, and that if more
                    people were busy fighting little wars, they might not be involved in fighting
                    big ones.”<ptr target="#note32" xml:id="nr32" n="32"/> But Gygax found far more
                    inspiration in Wells than a stance on the importance of wargaming. Gygax praises
                    Wells’s game for its formative role in the development of his tabletop games:
                            <ab><emph rend="italic">Little Wars</emph> influenced my development of
                        both the <emph rend="italic">Chainmail</emph> miniatures rules and the <emph
                            rend="italic">Dungeons &amp; Dragons</emph> fantasy roleplaying game.
                        For example, it established the concept of a burst radius for cannon rounds,
                        an idea that was translated into both the <emph rend="italic"
                            >Chainmail</emph> catapult missile diameters and the areas of effect for
                        Fireballs in D&amp;D. <ptr target="#note33" xml:id="nr33" n="33"/></ab> Not
                    only does this foreword indicate quite a high degree of validation of Wells’s
                    work as spoken from the mouth of one of gaming culture's gods, but by declaring
                    the adaptation of Wells’s rules for his own influential works, Gygax reveals a
                    transmission history of common game mechanics. Burst radius and Area of Effect
                    have proliferated beyond tabletop gaming into the digital world of video games
                    by way of <emph rend="italic">Dungeon &amp; Dragons</emph>, and become
                    colloquialized into the common acronym AoE. Examples of the reliance on the
                    concept of AoE as Wells and Gygax propose are numerous: <emph rend="italic"
                        >World of Warcraft</emph>, <emph rend="italic">Final Fantasy Tactics</emph>,
                    and <emph rend="italic">Dragon Age</emph> are popular and prime examples of the
                    simple application of Euclidean geometry as Wells prescribes it for
                    operationalizing cannonfire or any analogous mechanism a game may desire to
                    express. How far the concept has come from lengths of string and a spring-loaded
                        toy!<ptr target="#note34" xml:id="nr34" n="34"/></p>
                <p>We mention Gygax not to divert interest from how innovative and interesting <emph
                        rend="italic">Little Wars</emph> is in and of itself, but to include an
                    additional motive for its study and its relevance to game studies. The passage
                    above shows how the theory of transmission, well known to textual scholars and
                    editors, can be seen as an overt force that works in a unique way when compared
                    to traditional textual transmission. The way a concept such as a rule carries
                    through time and through different works by different authors highlights just
                    how much games, although narratives in their own right, are also just as much
                    texts in a physical and phenomenological sense, capable of being adapted and
                    interpreted (as we do in the streamlined rules), but also borrowed from,
                    modernized, and, for lack of a better phrase, <emph rend="italic">played
                        with</emph>. </p>
                <p><emph rend="italic">Little Wars </emph>is also special because of the previously
                    mentioned “development diary” in chapter two. This chapter traces Wells’s
                    journey in not only creating but revising the rules of <emph rend="italic"
                        >Little Wars</emph>; a book of rules was already revolutionary at the time,
                    but that he described his process shows what a careful and thoughtful game
                    designer Wells was. Not only can we view Wells’s rulebook in terms of what it
                    has contributed towards the games that have come after it, but <emph
                        rend="italic">Little Wars</emph> points back to itself, investing space in
                    its own process of creation and refinement as a game worth carrying forward.
                </p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Editorial Decisions</head>
                <p/>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>The XML</head>
                <p/>
            </div>
        </body>

        <back>
            <div type="notes">
                <note xml:id="note1">Jon Peterson, <emph rend="italic">Playing at the World: A
                        History of Simulating Wars, People and Fantastic Adventures From Chess to
                        Role-Playing Games</emph>. 2nd ed. (Unreason Press, 2012), 16.</note>
                <note xml:id="note2">Esther MacCallum-Stewart, “Wargaming (as) Literature,” <emph
                        rend="italic">Zones of Control: Perspectives on Wargaming</emph>. Eds. Pat
                    Harrigan and Matthew G. Kirschenbaum (Cambridge: The MIT Press, 2016),
                    556.</note>
                <note xml:id="note3">H. G. Wells,<emph rend="italic"> Little Wars</emph> (London:
                    Frank Palmer, 1913), 63-4. </note>
                <note xml:id="note4">Wells, <emph rend="italic">Little Wars</emph>, 96-7.</note>
                <note xml:id="note5">Kenneth D. Brown speculates that Wells named this character
                    Britten after the influential toy maker William Britain. “Modelling for War? Toy
                    Soldiers in Late Victorian and Edwardian Britain.” <emph rend="italic">Journal
                        of Social History</emph> 24: 252.</note>
                <note xml:id="note6">H. G. Wells, <emph rend="italic">The New Machiavelli</emph>
                    (New York: Duffard and Company, 1910), 79.</note>
                <note xml:id="note7">Peterson, “A Game Out of All Control,” 10. </note>
                <note xml:id="note8">Brown, 237.</note>
                <note xml:id="note9">Jon Peterson, <emph rend="italic">Playing at the World</emph>,
                    265.</note>
                <note xml:id="note10">Like Wells, Robert Louis Stevenson wrote about his imagined
                    battles after the game as if he was reporting on the war. Unlike Wells,
                    Stevenson was not famous when he was playing his wargames. However, a portion of
                    Stevenson’s game descriptions were published as “Stevenson at Play: With an
                    Introduction by Lloyed Osbourne” in <emph rend="italic">Scribner’s
                        Magazine</emph> in December 1898.</note>
                <note xml:id="note11">Brown, 241.</note>
                <note xml:id="note12">H.G. Wells, <emph rend="italic">Floor Games</emph> (London:
                    Frank Palmer, 1911), 71.</note>
                <note xml:id="note13">James Opie, <emph rend="italic">Britains Toy Soldiers: the
                        History and Handbook, 1893-2013</emph> (South Yorkshire: Pen and Ink
                    Military, 2016): 75.</note>
                <note xml:id="note14">Wells, <emph rend="italic">Little Wars</emph>, 99-100.</note>
                <note xml:id="note15"> Jon Peterson, “A Game Out of All Proportion: How a Hobby
                    Miniaturized War,”<emph rend="italic"> Zones of Control</emph>, 10.</note>
                <note xml:id="note16">Wells, <emph rend="italic">Floor Games</emph>, 36.</note>
                <note xml:id="note17">W. Warren Wagar, <emph rend="italic">H.G. Wells: Traversing
                        Time</emph> (Middletown, CT: Wesleyan University Press, 2004), 135.</note>
                <note xml:id="note18">Interestingly, aside from a man with a bow and arrow on the
                    first page of chapter one, all of the marginal illustrations appear to depict
                    British soldiers. However, William Britain’s toy soldiers often “came in sets of
                    opposing armies, and their production provides a virtual catalogue of European
                    and extra-European conflict between 1985 and 1914.” Brown, 245.</note>
                <note xml:id="note19">Peterson, <emph rend="italic">Playing at the World</emph>,
                    113.</note>
                <note xml:id="note20"> Peterson,<emph rend="italic">Playing at the World</emph>,
                    268.</note>
                <note xml:id="note21">Wells, <emph rend="italic">Little Wars</emph>, 99.</note>
                <note xml:id="note22"> In Cynthia Asquith’s autobiography, she reminisces about her
                    brother, Ego, playing <emph rend="italic">Little Wars</emph>: “There was a
                    remarkably uncomfortable phase when practically every inch of 62 Cadogan
                    Square--staircase and all--was given up to a war game invented by H. G. Wells
                    and played with toy mechanical guns and tin soldiers.” <emph rend="italic">Haply
                        I May Remember</emph> (J. Barrie, 1950), 169. </note>
                <note xml:id="note23">Susan Stewart, <emph rend="italic">On Longing: Narratives of
                        the Miniature, the Gigantic, the Souvenir, the Collection</emph> (London:
                    Duke University Press, 1993), 69. </note>
                <note xml:id="note24">Wells, <emph rend="italic">Little Wars</emph>, 97.</note>
                <note xml:id="note25">Isaac Asimov, “Foreword,” <emph rend="italic">Little
                        Wars</emph> (New York: The Macmillan Company, 1970), n.p.</note>
                <note xml:id="note26"> Wells, <emph rend="italic">Little Wars</emph>, 97.</note>
                <note xml:id="note27">H.G. Wells, <emph rend="italic">An Experiment in
                        Autobiography: Discoveries and Conclusions of a Very Ordinary Brain</emph>
                    (New York: The Macmillan Company, 1934), 74. </note>
                <note xml:id="note28">Wells, <emph rend="italic">An Experiment</emph>, 75.</note>
                <note xml:id="note29">Wells, <emph rend="italic">An Experiment</emph>, 76.</note>
                <note xml:id="note30">Wells, <emph rend="italic">An Experiment</emph>, 76.</note>
                <note xml:id="note31">Notably, even before World War I some people spoke out against
                    toy soldiers, including Oscar Wilde’s wife, Constance Lloyd; Brown, 246. Brown
                    and other scholars have also made causal connections between the popularization
                    of militarism in Britain during the years before 1914 and the coming war. </note>
                <note xml:id="note32">Gary Gygax, “Foreword,” <emph rend="italic">Little Wars</emph>
                    (Springbranch, TX: Skirmisher Publishing LLC, 2004), xxi.</note>
                <note xml:id="note33">Gary Gygax, xxi-xxii.</note>
                <note xml:id="note34">Wells credits <emph rend="italic">Little Wars</emph> to the
                    invention of toy cannons, and he recommends string as a measurement device
                    during game play. Developing “toy” technologies have continued to make wargaming
                    more sophisticated.</note>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>

</tei>
