<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader xml:lang="en">
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Streamlined Rules for H. G. Wells' <emph rend="italic"
                        >LITTLE WARS</emph></title>
                <editor key="lepianka">Nigel Lepianka</editor>
                <editor key="stover">Deanna Stover</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Creation and Encoding</resp>
                    <name xml:id="ed">Nigel Lepianka and Deanna Stover</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2016</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>Scholarly Editing: The Annual of the Association for Documentary
                    Editing</authority>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>http://www.scholarlyediting.org</addrLine>
                </address>
                <publisher>Association for Documentary Editing</publisher>
                <publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
                <distributor>
                    <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>http://cdrh.unl.edu</addrLine>
                    </address>
                </distributor>
                <date>2016</date>
                <availability>
                    <p>Scholarly Editing: The Annual of the Association for Documentary Editing is
                        freely distributed by the Association for Documentary Editing and the Center
                        for Digital Research in the Humanities at the University of Nebraska-Lincoln
                        and licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike
                        3.0 Unported License</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="j">Scholarly Editing: The Annual of the Association for Documentary
                    Editing</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name xml:id="ag">Amanda Gailey</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name xml:id="awj">Andrew Jewell</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name xml:id="ng">Nicole Gray</name>
                </respStmt>
                <idno type="vol">38</idno>
                <idno type="ISSN">2167-1257</idno>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <note>Born digital.</note>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change who="lepianka" when="2016-11-18">Begin encoding of streamlined rules.</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <head>Preface</head>
                <p>This section represents an attempt to streamline the rules presented in Little
                    Wars. In some sections, Wells’s rules are unclear or in need of further
                    explanation. This is most apparent in the rules for the mêlée, where some
                    questions may arise as to which player may act first, or how certain decisions
                    for the loss of units are made. We have made notes in the text of Little Wars
                    where these moments occur, and the streamlined rules presented here attempt to
                    resolve these complications. This rule list might be considered a better option
                    for reference should one desire to play Little Wars, as it condenses Wells’s
                    sometimes verbose and disorganized instructions. </p>
            </div>


            <div>
                <head><label>1.</label> The Forces</head>
                <list rend="bulleted">
                    <head><label>1.1</label> The Units</head>
                    <item>There are two types of units, infantry and cavalry. Infantry may move up
                        to 1 foot, while cavalry may move up to 2 feet. Other than movement speed,
                        infantry and cavalry follow the same rules.</item>
                    <item>A space of 1/16 of an inch should be kept between all units and terrain. A
                        unit may never be placed inside any part of the Country, including
                        houses.</item>
                    <item>When a unit moves within 1/8 of an inch of an enemy unit, it must stop its
                        movement and is considered in <emph rend="italic">contact</emph> with the
                        enemy unit.</item>
                    <item>If a unit is not within one move of at least half of the remaining
                        friendly units, it is considered <emph rend="italic">isolated</emph>.</item>
                    <item>Units may retreat from battle by crossing their own backline. They are
                        removed from play, but may still be counted as alive and uncaptured when
                        determining points for the battle.</item>
                    <item>Units may be captured by the enemy and made <emph rend="italic"
                            >prisoners</emph>. <list>
                            <item><emph rend="italic">Prisoners</emph> may not participate in <emph
                                    rend="italic">mêlées</emph>, cannot escort other prisoners, and
                                do not count when determining whether or not a cannon is <emph
                                    rend="italic">manned</emph> or captured.</item>
                            <item>One friendly unit may escort up to 7 enemy <emph rend="italic"
                                    >prisoners</emph> within 6 inches of it.</item>
                            <item>Escorted <emph rend="italic">prisoners</emph> are moved by the
                                opposing player on their turn, but unescorted <emph rend="italic"
                                    >prisoners</emph> may be moved normally by their player. </item>
                            <item>A unit is no longer considered a <emph rend="italic"
                                    >prisoner</emph> if it makes it to its friendly backline. It is
                                removed from the battlefield if it is taken to the enemy backline.
                                These changes are made during the Aftermath stage of a player’s
                                turn.</item>
                        </list>
                    </item>
                </list>

                <list rend="bulleted">
                    <head><label>1.2</label> The Cannons</head>
                    <item>Requires at least 4 friendly units within 6 inches to be considered <emph
                            rend="italic">manned</emph> by that side. A cannon must be <emph
                            rend="italic">manned</emph> in order to be moved or fired.</item>
                    <item> Can either be moved or fired in the same turn, not both. </item>
                    <item>Cannons may not be fired during the first turn of the game.</item>
                    <item>Can fire up to 4 shots during a turn. After firing its last shot, the
                        cannon cannot be aimed or adjusted and one friendly unit within 6 inches
                        must be placed on each side of the cannon near the wheels. </item>
                    <item>When being moved, at least four men who are with the cannon must move up
                        with it to its new position, and be placed within six inches of it in its
                        new position. The cannon may move the speed of the 4 fastest units moving
                        with it. The muzzle of the cannon must point backward toward the direction
                        it came from.</item>
                    <item>A shot from a cannon kills the first unit it touches as well as any other
                        unit that falls because of it. A unit that cannot stand on its own and would
                        full if unsupported after a shot is considered killed. </item>
                    <item>While firing, cannons may be rotated around the middle point of its wheel
                        axle to take aim while any friendly units within 6 inches may be laid down
                        to allow the gun to fire.</item>
                </list>
            </div>

            <div>
                <head><label>2.</label> The Battle</head>
                <list rend="bulleted">
                    <head><label>2.1</label> Setup</head>
                    <item>Before playing, the players will need to setup the battlefield and the
                        forces that will fight upon it.</item>
                    <item>Ensure that each player has a way of measuring distances in inches and
                        feet. Two pieces of string, one measuring two feet and the other six inches
                        will suffice.</item>
                    <item>Each player must determine the composition of their forces between
                        infantry, cavalry, and cannons. A standard game has each side with forces
                        with a total value of 150 points, though larger or smaller battles may be
                        fought as well. Infantry are 1 point, cavalry are 1 ½ points, and cannons
                        are 10 points.</item>
                    <item>Players will flip a coin to decide who shall arrange the Country. The
                        winner may place obstacles and cover to represent houses, trees, hills, etc
                        anywhere they wish over the battlefield. If any pieces of the Country are
                        bumped or moved during the turn, they must be placed back to their original
                        position immediately. </item>
                    <item>The player who did not arrange the Country will choose which side they
                        will fight from, determining which end of the battlefield will be their back
                        line.</item>
                </list>
            </div>

            <div>
                <head><label>2.2</label>Deployment</head>
                <list rend="bulleted">
                    <item>Once the players have chosen their forces and arranged the Country, it is
                        time for them to set up their armies and prepare for battle. The following
                        steps outline this process. </item>
                    <item>The players flip another coin to determine which shall go first. </item>
                    <item>The first player will arrange their forces along their back line. Units
                        not placed on the back line must be placed as close as possible and measure
                        distance for movement on their first turn as if they started on the back
                        line. The second player will then do the same.</item>
                    <item>Alternately, if some way of hiding the deployments can be arranged (such
                        as with a curtain between the two sides), then both sides may deploy their
                        forces at the same time. After both sides have finished, the deployments are
                        revealed and the players begin taking turns starting with the first
                        player.</item>
                </list>
            </div>

            <div>
                <head><label>2.3</label>Turns</head>
                <list rend="bulleted">
                    <item>A player’s turn will consist of several phases outlined below. These
                        phases must be resolved in order. After the Aftermath stage of a player’s
                        turn has finished, the next player will start the Command phase of their
                        turn. </item>
                    <item><label>2.3.1Command:</label> In this phase, the player will move their
                        cannons and units across the battlefield as well as fire their cannons. This
                        phase is timed, with an allowance of determined by the size of the original
                        forces as follows: 1 minute for every 30 units and 1 minute for each cannon.
                        Warnings should be given at 2 minutes, 1 minute, and 30 seconds. A player
                        may not interact with any cannon or unit until the timer starts and must
                        immediately stop once the timer expires. Every cannon and unit may be
                        activated during this phase as the rules and time permits. <list
                            rend="bulleted">
                            <item><label>Activate Cannons:</label> Any <emph rend="italic"
                                    >manned</emph> cannons controlled by the current player must be
                                moved/fired before any of their units. The only exception being
                                units that are moved up with a cannon after it moves.</item>
                            <item>Activate Units: After cannons have been moved/fired, any and all
                                units may be moved across the battlefield up to their speed value (1
                                foot for infantry, 2 feet for cavalry). Any units that are
                                considered in <emph rend="italic">contact</emph> after moving will
                                trigger a <emph rend="italic">mêlée</emph> in the next phase.</item>
                        </list>
                    </item>
                    <item><label>2.3.2 Hand-to-Hand Fighting:</label> In this phase, the players
                        will resolve the outcome of any mêlées that were triggered from the previous
                        phase. The following steps will be repeated as needed for every mêlée on the
                        battlefield. This phase is not timed. <list rend="bulleted">
                            <item><label>Choose mêlée:</label> The current player selects one of
                                their units that is in contact with an enemy unit. This will be the
                                center point of the <emph rend="italic">mêlée</emph> for the
                                following steps.</item>
                            <item><label>Determine Forces:</label> Each unit within 6 inches from
                                the center point of the <emph rend="italic">mêlée</emph> will be
                                counted for each force. If both sides are equal, isolation is not a
                                factor and the players may move on to the Resolve mêlée step. </item>
                            <item><label>Determine Isolation:</label> If the number of units in a
                                    <emph rend="italic">mêlée</emph> for each side are not equal,
                                the players must determine if the inferior force is <emph
                                    rend="italic">isolated</emph> measuring from the center point of
                                the <emph rend="italic">mêlée</emph>. If any unit of the inferior
                                force is considered isolated, the entire force is isolated.</item>
                            <item><label>Resolve mêlée:</label> This step is where the casualties
                                and <emph rend="italic">prisoners</emph> are determined for the
                                    <emph rend="italic">mêlée</emph>. If the forces are equal or the
                                inferior side is not <emph rend="italic">isolated</emph>, each unit
                                kills an opposing unit if it can and then is killed. This continues
                                until no more units of an opposing side are within the <emph
                                    rend="italic">mêlée</emph>. If the inferior force is <emph
                                    rend="italic">isolated</emph>, a number of their units become
                                    <emph rend="italic">prisoners</emph> equal to the difference
                                between the forces. The remaining units then kill one unit and die
                                as outlined above. The current player determines which units (of
                                either side) are made <emph rend="italic">prisoners</emph> and which
                                are killed during a <emph rend="italic">mêlée</emph>.</item>
                        </list>
                    </item>
                    <item><label>2.3.3 Aftermath: </label>After all <emph rend="italic"
                            >mêlées</emph> have been resolved, some steps need to be taken to
                        determine the new state of the battle. Each player must perform the
                        following steps for their units. <list rend="bulleted">
                            <item><label>Determine Status of Cannons:</label> During this step,
                                players determine which cannons are currently <emph rend="italic"
                                    >manned</emph> by each force. If a cannon has no friendly units
                                and at least 4 enemy units within 6 inches and those enemy units
                                have crossed the cannon’s wheel axis, that cannon is captured and is
                                considered <emph rend="italic">manned</emph> by the enemy force. The
                                enemy player may use this cannon as if it were part of their force
                                on their next turn.</item>
                            <item><label>Determine Status of Prisoners:</label> With units moving
                                across the battlefield and being killed, that status of <emph
                                    rend="italic">prisoners</emph> may have changed. During this
                                step, both players determine which of their captured <emph
                                    rend="italic">prisoners</emph> are currently escorted. Escorted
                                    <emph rend="italic">prisoners</emph> are moved by the opposing
                                player on their turn, but unescorted <emph rend="italic"
                                    >prisoners</emph> may be moved normally by their player. <emph
                                    rend="italic">Prisoners</emph> that return to their own backline
                                are no longer considered <emph rend="italic">prisoners</emph> during
                                this step and any <emph rend="italic">prisoners</emph> brought to
                                the enemy backline are removed from play as well. </item>
                        </list>
                    </item>
                </list>
            </div>

            <div>
                <list>
                    <head>3. Game Modes</head>
                    <item><label>3.1 Fight to the Finish</label> This is the standard way to play
                        the game. The objective is to kill, capture, or drive back the entirety of
                        your enemy’s forces. Both sides continue to fight until either all units of
                        one side retreat, are killed/captured, or both sides are reduced to below 15
                        units (which results in a draw).</item>
                    <item><label>3.2 The Blow at the Rear</label> The objective of this game mode is
                        to be the first player to get at least three of their units to the
                        opponent’s back line. At this point, the defeated player has suffered a
                        strategic loss and has 6 of their turns to retreat as many units as possible
                        over their back line. Any units that have not retreated after the 6th turn
                        are captured by the victor. This game mode is designed for a smaller and
                        more constrained Country and is much shorter than a Fight to the Finish. </item>
                    <item><label>3.3 Defensive</label> In this game mode, one player is designated
                        as the defender while the other is the attacker. The objective for the
                        attacker is to get ¼ of their original units to the defender’s back line,
                        while the defender must prevent this. The defender must have a force that is
                        ⅔ as strong as the attacker. After setting up the Country, the player who
                        chooses their side will become the defender. The defender will become first
                        player (without a coin flip) and may deploy their units anywhere on their
                        side, as long as they are not within one move of the center of the
                        battlefield. The attacker will then deploy their units, which may be within
                        one move of their back line. The defender may ignore the restriction on
                        cannons firing on the first turn and may open fire immediately.</item>
                    <item><label>3.4 Campaign</label>Several battles may be strung together to
                        create a campaign, where players will score points at the end of each battle
                        adding them up until an ultimate victor is found. All three types of battles
                        may be fought in any combination during a campaign. Once a battle is over,
                        points are awarded to each side as follows: <list rend="bulleted">
                            <item>The winning side gains 100 points (each side gets 50 points on a
                                draw).</item>
                            <item>Each side gains points for the value of each of their remaining
                                units that are alive and uncaptured. The players get 1 point for
                                infantry, 1 ½ points for cavalry, and 10 points for each cannon they
                                currently control or are in a position to take.</item>
                            <item>Each side gains ½ point for each prisoner captured and ½ point for
                                each prisoner the enemy captured. </item>
                        </list> Depending on the number of games desired in the campaign, a point
                        value is determined (usually 200, 300, or 400). At the end of any battle
                        where a player’s new point total would exceed their opponent’s total by this
                        amount, that player has won the campaign. </item>
                </list>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>

</TEI>
